Register of the Robert Le Baron Papers, 1946-1983
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert Le Baron Papers,
1946-1983
84027
LeBaron, Robert
4 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 phonotape cassette. (2.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Biographical sketches, reminiscences, speeches, letters, appointment books, memoranda, memorabilia, and photographs, relating to the development of U.S. atomic weapons, and to peaceful uses of atomic energy.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1984.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
U.S. Atomic Energy Commission.; United States. Dept. of Defense.; Nuclear energy--United States.; Nuclear weapons.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--Defenses.; Phonotapes.; Nuclear energy.
Biographical Note
1891, Oct. 31 Born, Binghamton, N.Y.
1913 B.S., Union College, Schenectady, New York
1917 M.S., Princeton University, New Jersey
1919 Research, Marie Curie, Sorbonne, Paris, France
1926 Married, Peggy Bancroft
1942-1944 Consultant, "Dollar-a-Year," United States Government
1949-1954 Chairman, Military Liaison Committee, United States Government Deputy to the Secretary of Defense on Atomic Energy, United States Government Alternate Member, Combined Policy Committee, United States Government
1955 Founder, LeBaron Associates
1961 Founder, Norabel Fund
1967 Founder, LeBaron Foundation
1983, Mar. 5 Died, Washington, D. C.
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1946-1983. (Box 1)
  Clippings and miscellany relating to the life of Robert LeBaron, arranged alphabetically by form.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1952-1959. (Box 1-2)
  Drafts, outlines and printed copies of speeches and lectures by Robert LeBaron, with correspondence, notes and materials relating to them, arranged chronologically by date of writing.
- MILITARY LIAISON COMMITTEE FILE, 1949-1952. (Box 2-4)
  Correspondence, appointment books, writings and miscellany, all relating to Robert LeBaron's tenure as chairman, arranged alphabetically by form.
- LE BARON ASSOCIATES FILE, 1955-1962. (Box 4)
  Correspondence, memoranda and writings, all relating to Robert LeBaron's tenure as consultant, arranged alphabetically by form.
- LE BARON FOUNDATION FILE, 1967-1972?. (Box 4)
  Clippings, memoranda, and miscellany, all relating to Robert LeBaron's participation in the Foundation, arranged alphabetically by form.
- OVERSIZE, 1949-1981. (Box 5-6)
  Scrapbooks of correspondence, clippings, music scores, photographs and miscellany.
- PHONOTAPE, c. 1970. (Cabinet Cassette cabinet.)
  Tape recording of Robert LeBaron in interview.
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL, 1946-1983
  - General
    - Clippings, 1982 (Box 1., Folder 1)
    - "The Eighth Day." Screenplay, clippings, photographs relating to Cinerama film production on atomic energy. LeBaron retained as consultant, 1956-1958 (Folder 2)
  - Biography
    - Hager, Alice. Correspondence relating to Hager's writing of biographical piece, 1957-1962 (Folder 3)
    - Root, Lin, "Robert LeBaron: Man of many Talents," n.d. Typescript (Folder 4)
    - Root, Lin, "A People's Program," c. 1970. Draft. Includes correspondence and transcript of LeBaron interview (Folder 5)
    - Snell, Adams, "From Business - to Bach - to Business: Bob LeBaron," May 9, 1946. Typescript (Folder 6)
  - Death. Obituary; letter of condolence to Mrs. Robert LeBaron; remarks by Senator Mark O. Hatfield, 1983 (Folder 7)
  - Reminiscences, 1968 (Folder 8)
  - Resumes
    - General (Folder 9)
    - Who's Who (Folder 10)
  - Tributes. Congressional Record, October 28, 1981. In honor of 90th birthday (Folder 11)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1952-1959
  - General. Pre-speech materials (Box 1., Folder 12)
  - Untitled, speech, Purdue University?, April 1952. Typescript. Relates to military and civilian applications of atomic energy. Includes preparatory materials (Folder 13)
  - "Your Future in the Atomic Age," speech, The Lutheran Student Seminar, April 13, 1954. Typescript (Folder 14)
  - Untitled, speech, YWCA, May 10, 1954. Typescript. Relates to civilian application of atomic energy (Folder 15)
  - "The Peaceful Atom," speech, The Trane Company, May 20, 1954. Printed copy (Folder 16)
  - "Women and the Peaceful Atom," address, National Federation of Republican Women, September 22, 1954. Typescript (Box 2., Folder 1)
  - "The Peaceful Atom," speech, Union Collge, November 17, 1954. Outline (Folder 2)
  - Untitled, speech, American Association for the United Nations, Inc., February 22, 1955. Outline. Relates to the development of the hydrogen bomb. Includes printed editorial: Cousins, Norman, "The Devil's Bargain Basement," Saturday Review, n.d. (Folder 3)
  - Untitled, speech, Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics Laboratory, February 25, 1955. Memorandum telling of the above. No prepared speech or notes (Folder 4)
  - "Our New Frontiers," speech, Eighty-fifth Annual Commencement Address, Theil College, May 29, 1955. Typescript. Address given upon receipt of Honorary Degree of Doctor of Science. Includes draft, March 29, 1955; memorandum of The Joint Faculty-Trustee Committee on Honorary Degrees of Theil College (Folder 5)
  - Untitled, speech, The Cosmos Club, April 11?, 1955. Outline. Relates to the civilian and military role of atomic energy (Folder 6)
  - Untitled, speech, April 13, 1955. Outline. Relates to the civilian and military role of atomic energy. Perhaps a final draft for The Cosmos Club speech of April 11?, 1955 (Folder 7)
  - "The Atom Today: The Present Status of Peacetime Developments," speech, Gannon College Engineering Project Dinner, July 13, 1955. Draft (Folder 8)
  - "Decision at H-Day," book proposal, July 9, 1958. Draft (Folder 9)
- MILITARY LIAISON COMMITTEE FILE, 1949-1954
  - Appointment books, 1951-1952
    - 1951 (Box 2., Folder 10)
    - 1952 (Folder 11)
  - Biographical data. Interview, correspondence, resume and clipping, 1953-1976 (Folder 12)
  - Calendar, 1954? (Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1954. Includes personal correspondence
    - General. Correspondence neither to nor from LeBaron (Box 3., Folder 1)
    - Aircraft Industries Association (Folder 2)
    - Bancroft, Ethel (Folder 3)
    - Bendetsen, Karl R. (Folder 4)
    - Cammack, Howard H. (Folder 5)
    - Campbell, Levin H. (Folder 6)
    - Campbell, Majorie (Folder 7)
    - Clarkson, P.W. (Folder 8)
    - Cockcroft, J.D. (Folder 9)
    - Cox, Carl C. (Folder 10)
    - Crump, George Mayo (Folder 11)
    - Dodson, Richard W. (Folder 12)
    - Doherty, Henry A. (Folder 13)
    - Eisenhower, D. D. (Folder 14)
    - Fuller, Jean W. (Folder 15)
    - Hannah, John A. (Folder 16)
    - Ide, Chandler and Helen (Folder 17)
    - Lawrence, E. O. (Folder 18)
    - Luckenbach, W. F., Jr. (Folder 19)
    - Machinery and Allied Products Institute (Folder 20)
    - Midkiff, Frank E. (Folder 21)
    - Moore, Ralph O. (Folder 22)
    - Nash, Frank C. (Folder 23)
    - Penny, William (Folder 24)
    - Pick, Vernon (Folder 25)
    - Poister, C. E. (Folder 26)
    - Prentice, Howard A. (Folder 27)
    - Ramsey, D. C. (Folder 28)
    - Russel, James S. (Folder 29)
    - Schuyler, C. V. R. (Folder 30)
    - Shutt, R. (Folder 31)
    - Solandt, Ormond (Folder 32)
    - Steffan, Roger (Folder 33)
    - Stewart, Charles W. (Folder 34)
    - Strauss, Alice (Folder 35)
    - Teleprompter of Washington, Inc. (Folder 36)
    - Teller, Edward (Folder 37)
    - United States Atomic Energy Commission, General Advisory Committee (Folder 38)
    - Vesper, Howard and Ruth (Folder 39)
    - Wilson, Charles E. (Folder 40)
    - Wilson, R. C. (Folder 41)
    - Winkleblack, R. K. (Folder 42)
    - Wirth, Harold E. (Folder 43)
    - Wright, E. K. (Folder 44)
  - Memoranda, 1949-1954 (Folder 45)
  - Miscellany. Notes, itinerary, c. 1949 (Folder 46)
  - Press Releases, 1954 (Folder 47)
  - Printed matter. Pamphlet on particle accelerators, 1947 (Folder 48)
  - Roster. Atomic Energy Council members and Military Liaison Committee members, 1949 (Folder 49)
  - Scrapbook. Letters of resignation, clippings, memoranda, press releases, photograph, 1949-1954 (Folder 50)
  - Speeches and Writings, 1952-1954
    - Untitled, speech, Joint Civilian Orientation Conference, April 2, 1952. Typescript. Relates to atomic weaponry, its production, implementation and effect on military strategy. Includes note cards (Folder 51)
    - Untitled, speech, September 1952. Typescript. Second draft, prepared by Coonley for distribution. Relates to atomic energy and weaponry. Includes memorandum with regard to Coonley's efforts (Folder 52)
    - Untitled, speech, Industrial Power Development, Joint Congressional Committee (Atomic Energy), June 25, 1953. Typescript. Relates to the military and the application of atomic energy to industry (Folder 53)
    - "Atom Power for Homes in Five Years," U.S. News and World Report, June 25, 1954. Interview with LeBaron. Printed copy. Includes correspondence with readers (Folder 54)
  - Subject File, 1949-1954
    - Appointment as Chairman Military Liaison Committee, 1949. Memoranda, press release, correspondence, 1949-1950 (Folder 55)
    - Resignation as Chairman Military Liaison Committee, 1954. Memorandum, correspondence (Folder 56)
    - Security. Memorandum, 1954; Personnel Security Questionnaire, 1949? (Box 4., Folder 1)
- LE BARON ASSOCIATES FILE, 1955-1962
  - Biographical. Resumes (Box 4., Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1956. Strauss, Lewis (Folder 3)
  - Memoranda, 1955-1962 (Folder 4)
  - Press Releases. Department of Defense?, Joint Committee on Atomic Energy (Folder 5)
  - Prospectus (Folder 6)
  - Roster. Committee on Commercial Uses of Atomic Energy (Folder 7)
  - Speeches and Writings, 1955-1958
    - Untitled, essay, n.d. Typescript. Relates to industrial applications of classified research (Folder 8)
    - "A Philosophical Approach to Long Range Atomic Investments," speech, National Industrial Conference Board Training Course, September 14, 1955. Outline and handwritten notes (Folder 9)
    - "Investing in Industrial Atomic Energy," speech, Commercial and International Developments in Atomic Energy, Atomic Industrial Forum, September 27, 1955. Typescript, printed copy and agenda (Folder 10)
    - "The Latin American Market Potential for Atomic Investment," speech, Atomic Energy in Industry, National Industrial Conference Board, Inc., October 27, 1955. Typescript and printed copy (Folder 11)
    - "Investment Opportunities," speech, Atomic Energy Course for Management, National Industrial Conference Board, Inc., November 17, 1955. Outline (Folder 12)
    - "Radiation's Share in the Atomic Future," speech, Quartermaster Corps Radiation and Sterilization of Foods Symposium, January 23, 1956. Typescript (Folder 13)
    - Untitled, speech, Daystrom Presidents' Meeting, Essex Club, May 25, 1956. Outline (Folder 14)
    - "Atomic Energy: Probable Impact on Investments," lectures, The Life Officers Investment Seminar, American Life Convention, June 18-29, 1956. Outlines for two lectures (Folder 15)
    - "Outlook for Investment," lecture, National Industrial Conference Board, Inc., October 4, 1956. Outline. Includes draft (Folder 16)
    - Untitled, speech, The Latest Prospects for Economic Nuclear Power - II, National Industrial Conference Board, Inc., March 14-15, 1957. Outline (Folder 17)
    - "Outline for Investments," lecture, Atomic Energy Course for Management, National Industrial Conference Board, Inc., April 1-6, 1957. Outline (Folder 18)
    - "A Public Forum for National Atomic Policy," speech, District of Columbia Bar, October 8, 1957. Outline (Folder 19)
    - "The Investment Situation in Atomic Energy," speech, National Industrial Conference Board, Inc., October 11, 1957. Outline (Folder 20)
    - "Atomic Transport," speech, "Road Gang" Group - Jim Mann, November 7, 1957. Outline (Folder 21)
    - "What does `Sputnik' Portend?," speech, Philco International, January 31, 1958. Outline. Includes clippings, notes (Folder 22)
    - "A New Atomic Economy," speech, Atomic Energy Management Conference, Atomic Industrial Forum, National Industrial Conference Board, Inc., March 18, 1958. Typescript. Includes draft, and agenda for conference (Folder 23)
    - Untitled, lecture, Atomic Energy Course for Management, National Industrial Conference Board, Inc., April 18-19, 1958. Outline (Folder 24)
    - "What is the Future of Commercial Radiation?," speech, Atomic Energy in Industry, 7th Annual Conference, National Industrial Conference Board, Inc., April 9, 1959. Typescript (Folder 25)
  - Subject File
    - Atomic Energy Study Group, 1955. Correspondence, proposals, minutes, clippings (Folder 26)
    - Security. Correspondence, memoranda, classified reports receipts, all pertaining to LeBaron's security clearance (Folder 27)
- LE BARON FOUNDATION FILE, 1967-1972?
  - Clippings, 1967-1968 (Box 4., Folder 28)
  - Memoranda. Handwritten, typewritten, 1968 (Folder 29)
  - Printed Matter. Annual report of the LeBaron Foundation, 1972? (Folder 30)
- OVERSIZE, 1949-1981
  - Scrapbook, 1950-1981. Correspondence, clippings, invitations, photographs, music scores (Box 5.)
  - Scrapbooks, 1949-1963. Correspondence, clippings, invitations, photographs (Box 6.)
- PHONOTAPE, c. 1970
  - Compact cassette, 90 minutes. Tape recording of discussion between Lin Root?, Robert LeBaron and Peggy LeBaron (Cassette 1)